International Workers Order (IWO) Records 5276
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Reports, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    To the Plenary Session of the G.E.B. - September 14, 15, 16, 1940. New York. 27 pages. Discusses the threat of reaction, organizing campaign, district financing, Youngstown, Ohio lodges, consolidation, Brighton Beach area in Brooklyn, English and Jewish lodges.
  - Item 3: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1940; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 4)
    For the General Executive Board. 19 pages. Delivered at District Convention, discusses fascism, war, Social Security campaign, General Lodges, consolidation, New Jersey lodges. Also includes proposed draft resolution on consolidation, list of G.E.B. members, two pre-convention discussion issues "Our Tasks", "Resolution on the establishment of an IWO Home for the Ages", supplementary resolution on consolidation, Directives on applying the Policy of Consolidation.
- Reports, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    To the G.E.B., February 22-23, 1941. New York City. 9 pages. Discusses fascism, world politics, Dies Committee, raid on Philadelphia office, William Weiner's conviction, Jewish Section finances, (incomplete).
  - Item 2: Summary of Discussions, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Summary of Discussion on Report on Social Security Campaign by Brother Herbert Benjamin. 8 pages.
  - Item 3: Remarks of Herbert Benjamin, 1941; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Discussion on the Resolution Meeting of the G.E.B., I.W.O. New York, September 6, 1941. 18 pages. Discusses resolution to support U.S. fight against Nazism following Hitler's assault (see also Box 1, FF 8).
- Reports, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Report (2/7/42) 15 pages. Discusses organizational problems including consolidation, community lodges and councils, Williamsburg, New York Community Council, establishment of a membership department, recruiting, community centers, financing system.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Officers' Report to the G.E.B., February 7-8, 1942. 19 pages. Discusses fascism, political activities, service to unions, Dies Committee, Front Line Fighters Fund, Civilian Defense, youth activities, Stelmach Scroll, activities of Nationality Sections, and Departments, membership.
- Reports, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    "IWO & Its Tasks" - Report by Max Bedacht, General Secretary at the Functionaries Conference - August 24, 1942. 15 pages. Discusses Jewish Section problems, organizing congressional elections, Nationality Sections, and 4 page summary of this report.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1942; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Report on the State of the Order by Max Bedacht, General Secretary, IWO to the GEB - November 6-9, 1942. 22 pages. Discusses anti-fascist activities, war bonds, war propaganda, civilian defense, war relief, congressional elections, major IWO weaknesses, organizing, national group lodges, women's work, Negro communities, district functionnaires & staffs, also includes Bedacht's report on work for victory, motions on IWO work for victory and memo on the structure of the IWO.
- Reports, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1943; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Report to the GEB on the Progress of the Order during the year 1942. February 26-27, 1942. 32 pages. Discusses war activities, politics, fascism, Finnish-American Lodge in Norwood, MA re: red cross auxiliary, Front Line Fighters Fund, Aid to Russia, finances, postponement of convention, home for aged, Social Security, benefits, organizing, membership, licensing, departments, nationality sections, cultural activities.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1943; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 8)
    A memorandum on the problems of our youth work by Max Bedacht. 6 pages.
- Reports, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1943; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 9)
    "Our Civic and Organizations" Report to the GEB of the IWO, February 26, 1943. 24 pages. Discusses the Russians in the war effort, Nazism in North Africa, Fascism in America, Democracy, Dies Committee, sectarianism, functionaries, organizing, postponing convention, tribute to Peter Shipka - also includes.
  - Item 2: Resolutions in Action, 1943; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Adopted by GEB, September 25-26, 1943.
- Reports, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Item 1: Pre-Convention Discussion Reports, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 10)
    By W. Weiner, President & Max Bedacht, General Secretary - GEB, February 12-13, 1944. New York City. 31 pages.
  - Item 2: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Hotel Riverside Plaza, New York City, February 12-13, 1944. l8 pages and summary. Discusses fascism, education members on political matters, cultural work.
- Reports, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Item 1: Towards 175,000 members by the 6th National Convention, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 11)
    By Ben Gordon, Secretary, National Organization Department - Report given at G.E.B., IWO, February 12-13, 1944. 16 pages.
  - Item 2: Resolutions, 1944; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 11)
    G.E.B. resolutions passed at February 12-13, 1944 meeting. See also: Box 1, FF 11.
- Report to the General Council by Max Bedacht, General Secretary, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  New York, November 24-26, l944. Includes discussion on Fraternal Committee for the Reelection of President Roosevelt, elections, organizing drive, Negro equality & organizing, relief activities, social security.
- Reports, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Financial report, Report to the General Council of the IWO by the General Secretary - "The Order in 1944" 34.
  - Item 2: Our Anti-Fascist Task of Today, 1945; Pamphlet (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Report of Max Bedacht, General Secretary, to the General Council, September 15-16, 1945. 38 pages, 19 pages. Discusses post-war fight against fascism, including national unity, Social Security, election campaigns, Negro rights, fraternal insurance, youth, immigration, veterans.
- Reports, 1946 (Box 56, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 4)
    The Order in 1945 and its perspectives for 1946 - Report of Max Bedacht, General Secretary to the General Council, March 16-17, 1946. 23 pages and 8 pages statistics. Discusses work of Jewish Society, Ukrainian, Russian, Slovak, Hungarian, Italian, Polish, Croatian, Serbian, Carpatho-Russian, Spanish, Romanian, Greek, Finnish, general lodges, organizing campaign, Western Pennsylvania Drive, finances, Front Line Fighters Fund, Fascism, ideological mobilization, Wagner Health Bill.
  - Item 2: On Veterans Work, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 4)
    Report to the General Council by Jerry Trauber - March 16-17, 1946. 9 pages.
  - Item 3: Report by General Secretary Max Bedacht, 1946; Pamphlet (Box 56, Folder 4)
    Report of Max Bedacht, General Secretary, To the General Council Meeting of the IWO - September 7-8, 1946. 16 pages and 2 pages summary. Discusses Negro persecution, Social Security legislation, Fascist immigration, congressional elections, national society, lodges.
- Reports, 1947 (Box 56, Folder 5)
  Report by Sam Milgram to the General Council of the IWO - New York - March 1-2, l947. 31 pages. Discusses discrimination against Negroes, Jews, establishment of FEPC, second generation in lodges, "Youngstown Story".
- Reports, 1948 (Box 56, Folder 6)
  Section of Executive Secretary, Brother Sam Milgrom's Report to general Council, Sunday, March 14, l948. 6 pages. "Our English-Speaking Work" also a resolution on this subject, minutes of Committee on English-Speaking Work, March 24, l948. 4 pages.
- Reports, 1949 (Box 56, Folder 7)
  Report of Brother Peter Shipka, General Secretary-Treasurer to the General Council of the IWO held on November 12-13, l949. 25 pages. Discusses Examination Report of New York Insurance Department, financial, membership, expulsions, Dunne's Insurance Rep
- Reports, 1951 (Box 56, Folder 8)
  Report of the Officers Presented to the General Council, IWO, February 3-4, 1951 - Delivered by Peter Shipka, General Secretary-Treasurer. 21 pages. Discusses convention cancellation, liquidation, Report of Examiners of New York Insurance Department, In
- IWO Financial Data, 1930-1952 (Box 56, Folder 9)
  incomplete misc. financial data.
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Includes reports, speeches, resolutions, attendance lists, proceedings, bulletin
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Convention Documents, 1938-1947 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- President - Kent, Rockwell, 1940-1941 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  Two letters to Max Bedacht discusses Kent's book, "This Is My Own". Kent suggests trying to keep cost down so members (IWO) and others can afford it. Kent says how important education is for the IWO and "An important part of education is the reading of
- President, Kent, Rockwell, 1947-1948 (Box 56, Folder 10)
  Correspondence generally to and from Sam Milgrom, Executive Secretary re some legal matters, Hungarian celebrations, recruiting drive, meeting arrangements, Henry Wallace political campaign; 3/1/48 to Milgrom, "I believe that if we could get thru the iron
- President, Kent, Rockwell, 1949 (Box 56, Folder 11)
  Mostly with Sam Milgrom re meeting and speaking arrangements; re financial difficulties of those identified with the left wing in politics, 10/15/49; 12/10/49 statement to NAACP (National Association for the Advancement of Colored People) endorsing their
- President - Kent, Rockwell, 1950 (Box 56, Folder 12)
  With Milgrom re sending observers to the NAACP crusade meeting; celebrations of IWO's 20th Anniversary; NY Times quoted TASS (USSR) in Kent's speech in Moscow saying "that the United States government is not my government" and Kent's letter with corrected
- President - Kent, Rockwell - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 56, Folder 13)
  Includes statement, appeal, articles.
- General Secretary - Bedacht, Max, 1938-1948 (Box 56, Folder 14)
  August 25, l942 memo from Gene Kahn, National Fraternal Congress to Bedacht enclosing list of organizations of National Fraternal Congress, Kahn explains "I have designated in pencil on the side names of IWO functionaries to whom I believe letters or memo
- General-Secretary - Bedacht, Max - Miscellaneous Mss. (Box 56, Folder 15)
  Includes "Our General Project for 1941-42"; "Our Anti-Fascist Task of Today," 1945; "Labor Fraternalism, A Guide to the Lodges and Members of the IWO," 29 pages; "Our Plan for Plenty,"; "The Concern of All..." - about National Health Act and miscellaneous
- General-Secretary - Bedacht, Max - Miscellaneous Mss. (Box 56, Folder 16)
- General-Secretary - Bedacht, Max - Miscellaneous Mss. (Box 56, Folder 17)
- Vice-President - Middleton, John E., 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence, form letters, speeches re civil service employee being questioned about his association with IWO; 8 page report, "For An Offensive On a Second European Front"; speech, "Defeat Fascism's Attack on the Soviet Union"; "The IWO and th
- Director of Organization - Milgrom, Sam, 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  March 1945 -June 1947. Correspondence re organizing new lodges; to various societies re meeting arrangements; national health bill legislation; membership drive, plans for general convention of Slovak Workers Society; organization of a city committee in M
- Director of Organization - Milgrom, Sam, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  July-September. Correspondence re membership; memo re proposed organizational changes; plans for separate Portuguese lodge in Fall River, Massachusetts; lists (1947) by Society giving number of lodges, and active builders.
- Director of Organization - Milgrom, Sam, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 3a)
  Johannes Steel Tour
- Director of Organization - Milgrom, Sam, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 3b)
  Correspondence with Steel re speaking tour, newsletters, broadsides and routine.
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Correspondence from United Resort Workers of America requesting IWO to hire union people for work in summer camps; from I. Gish, government employee, re criticism of Camp Kinderland by Sam Friedlander; other correspondence re Cam Kinderland; deportation
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Correspondence re deportation of Krishna Chandra and others because of past membership with IWO; Johnstown, Pennsylvania Lodge concerned re officers being accused of being Communists; 7 page outline "Attacks on the IWO," 6/19/50; memorandum re aid to IWO
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Memo to all societies re preparation of the appeal to secure a reversal of the liquidation decision, to Rockwell Kent requesting him to attend hearing in Albany; reinstatements of membership; and other correspondence re appeal hearings; memo including and
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Memo to all societies re preparation of the appeal to secure a reversal of the liquidation decision, to Rockwell Kent requesting him to attend hearing in Albany; reinstatements of membership; and other correspondence re appeal hearings; memo including
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave - Training School correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Includes correspondence, lists, financial reports, notes, programs for various training schools within the IWO, some of which were held at Camp Kinderland.
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave - Training School correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 57, Folder 1)
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave - Training School correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 57, Folder 2)
- General Director of Organization - Greene, Dave - Training School - Miscellaneous (Box 57, Folder 3)
  Includes mss. of reports re schools
- Executive Secretary - Milgrom, Sam, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Includes correspondence, minutes, form letters with
- Executive Secretary - Milgrom, Sam, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Minutes, 2/27/48 - Committee for Establishment of National Council of Lodges in Negro Communities; information on General Lodge Milk Fund Campaign; membership drive reports; reports and resolution on English-speaking work; tours; anti-lynching bill; state
- Executive Secretary - Milgrom, Sam, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Minutes, 2/27/48 - Committee for Establishment of National Council of Lodges in Negro Communities; information on General Lodge Milk Fund Campaign; membership drive reports; reports and resolution on English-speaking work; tours; anti-lynching bill
- Executive Secretary - Milgrom, Sam, 1948-1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Milgrom, Sam - Miscellaneous, 1946-1949 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Includes notes, memos, statistics, correspondence re Portuguese located in various geographical areas; lists of organizers by society; report on Parent-Children's Festival Tour; membership stats by society, 1946; letter to Milgram from J. Finley Wilson,
- Executive-Secretary - Benjamin, Herbert, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Includes "Resolution on Brother William Weiner," (President, IWO) to show support after his arrest and imprisonment, along with Earl Browder; 4 page form letter to all District and Section Secretaries re the building of membership in the organization; 6/2
- Executive Secretary - Benjamin - Mss., reports, speeches (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Re personnel policy; "The True Picture of America," 31 pages; "For Victory in the War Against the Fascist Axis," 11 pages; "Work Among the National Groups," 7 pages; "Review of Our Work, Our Shortcomings, Our Further Tasks,; 36 pages; Remarks by Benjamin
- Executive Secretary - Benjamin - Mss., reports, speeches, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  "We Give Aid and Comfort - Report on Income Disbursements Activities Response, Front Line Fighters Fund, 1941-42," unpaged; "To the GEB"; ll page memo re problems within the organization of the IWO; "Summary of Discussion, GEB, 4/27/42 by John Middleton,"
- Executive Secretary - Benjamin - Mss., reports, speeches, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  "Resolutions and Proposals on the Work of the Order Among National Groups," 4 pages; "Introduction to the Discussion on Resolution and Concrete Proposals for Improved National Group Work," 2/22/41, 13 pages; "Concrete Proposals Recommended for Adoption
- Executive Secretary = Benjamin - Mss., reports, speeches, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  "Labor's Battle, The Fight for William Weiner is the Fight For Freedom and the People's Welfare," 13 pages; Radio Speech, "The Plan For Plenty," 3/13/41, 30 pages; "For An Offensive On A Second European Front," 5/25/42, 8 pages; Speech "Unity for V
- Rymer, Harry - Administrative Department, 1944-1948 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  Includes routine office correspondence between Rymer and past and present employees
- Officers - General Information, 1944-1951 (Box 57, Folder 5)
  Lists of officers; requests for leaves of absence; resignations; list of dates of renewals for State Insurance Department licenses; memo re activities of IWO and other organizations, n.d.; memo from P. Shipka to William Karlin re collection of assessment
- Administrative Correspondence - General, 1938-1947 (Box 57, Folder 6)
  Mostly routine office correspondence re dues, membership eligibility, staff recommendations, life insurance and general operation of headquarters.
- Administrative Correspondence - General, 1938-1947 (Box 57, Folder 7)
- Administrative Correspondence - General, 1938-1947 (Box 57, Folder 8)
- Administrative Correspondence - General, 1938-1947 (Box 57, Folder 9)
- Alabama, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Includes one letter from George Glover to "Eddie", an organizer in Alabama. Discusses loss of IWO Charter in Alabama.
- Baltimore, 1940-1947 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  Correspondence re membership (suspension & reinstatements), local offices, recruitment drive, minutes of City Central Committee, for 8/23/44, letter to Milgrom from Baltimore, Secretary of City Central Committee Robert Meyers, re problems of the Committee
- Bronx, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Includes 33 page, "Report by H. Shiller, Secretary of the Bronx District Committee of the Jewish-American Section of the IWO to the Third Annual Convention of the Bronx District, held on Saturday and Sunday, March 27th and 28th, 1943." Report discusses J
- California, 1939-1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Correspondence re San Diego Local 577 members involved in strike with employers of a furniture company represented by United Furniture Workers - asking for IWO to investigate the situation and to give support; correspondence and legal documents re case of
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  Correspondence between Louise (Thompson) Patterson and Sam Milgrim and other re activities of lodges throughout the Chicago area, which includes Du Sable Lodge 751 and Midwest District (Miriam Cheifitz), re recruitment, IWO publications, social activities,
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  Correspondence between Louise (Thompson) Patterson and Sam Milgrim and other re activities of lodges throughout the Chicago area, which includes Du Sble Lodge 751 and Midwest District (Miriam Cheifitz), re recruitment, IWO publications, social activities,
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Chicago, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  Correspondence generally between officers of Michigan State Committee and Sam Milgrom re conflict between officers with Detroit lodges; Negro History Week Program plans; financial problems; recruitment drive; political campaign for Roosevelt; Romanian Fra
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Detroit, 1944-1948 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Florida, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  Correspondence between Edward Nelson, organizer and person interested in establishing a lodge in Florida once application for charter is approved.
- Indiana, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  Re IWO supporting Steel strikers; plans for state conference.
- Michigan, 1946-1947 (Box 7, Folder 11a)
  Correspondence re recruiting drive, lists of members, and routine.
- Minnesota, 1943-1946 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  Correspondence with Secretary of Lodge 596, St. Paul re election of officers and defense of the farmer labor movement; with member of Hotel and Restaurant Employees Union who is eager to establish a Scandinavian lodge in Minnesota; resolution on Black Mar
- New England District, 1940-1949 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  Includes "Proceedings, 1st Constitutional State Convention, IWO of Massachusetts, Held November 9 and 10, 1940," 17 p. mimeograph; correspondence between Sol Vail, Executive Secretary, New England District, Max Bedacht, General Secretary, and Sam Milgrom,
- New Haven, Connecticut, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  Correspondence between Harold Peters, New Haven organizer and later President of New Haven Lodge, and Sam Milgrom re recruitment and establishment of new lodge which was named "Frederick Douglass Society, IWO, Lodge 909."
- New Jersey, 1940-1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  Includes "Minutes, 5th Annual Convention, IWO, New Jersey, November 30th and December 1st, 1940," unpaged; correspondence between David Vines, Executive Secretary, New Jersey, IWO, and Milgrom and others re district budget; plans for the political campaign
- New York City, 1941-1945 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  Includes monthly program announcement for Lodge 500; lists of members of Hungarian, Carpatho-Russian, Greek, Roumanian, Yugoslavian, Puerto Rican, Spanish, Russian, Slovakian, and Italian members in New York City, 1942; correspondence with John Middleton,
- Ohio, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  Correspondence re support of the Price Control Bill; personnel problems with officers in Cleveland District; Toledo, Lodge 770 re problems with financial secretary office; Ohio District re political campaign for Roosevelt and state elections.
- Ohio, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  Correspondence re situation of IWO lodges in the Ohio Valley; 2 p. mimeograph of "Minutes, June 25, 1945, Cleveland City Committee of IWO"; also minutes for July 30, 1945 and September 24, 1945; and routine.
- Ohio, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  Correspondence re personnel needed for organizing in Ohio; plans for Health and Social Security Conference re bill, S. 1606; re organizing a City Central Committee in Youngstown; and routine.
- Ohio, 1946-1947 (Box 8, Folder 7a)
  Correspondence re recruiting drive in Ohio, largely correspondence with Cleveland City Committee; membership lists; and routine.
- Ohio, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 8)